Guide to the Sacvan Bercovitch papers, 1940-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sacvan Bercovitch papers 1940-2011
Bercovitch, Sacvan
36.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 26,000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00106
Language: Material is in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The collection was given as a gift by Sacvan Bercovitch from 1993-2011.
Biographical Note
Sacvan Bercovitch is a literary scholar and professor of English and American Literature and Language, Harvard University.
Collection Overview
Collection contains research notes, manuscripts on paper and floppy diskettes, and correspondence relating to the serial Cambridge History of American Literature, of which Bercovitch is general editor. Research notes chiefly relate to Bercovitch's work on colonial American literature and religion, particularly on the Puritans in New England, and American humor. Also includes drafts with corrections of A Cultural Model of Literary Studies, and Literary Context, both by Bercovitch. Another set of files consists of writings by others, curriculum vitae, and more correspondence pertaining to the Cambridge serial. Some correspondence and articles date from the 1940s and 1950s and were written by Bryna Bercovitch in Yiddish; English translations included. There are also some research materials and correspondence concerning Yiddish literature. Part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for Literary Historiography.
Subject Headings
Bercovitch, Sacvan; Bercovitch, Sacvan -- Cultural model of literary studies; Bercovitch, Sacvan -- Literary context; American literature -- 1783-1850 -- Study and teaching; American literature -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; American literature -- History and criticism; American wit and humor -- History and criticism; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; New England -- Intellectual life; Puritans -- New England; Religion and literature -- United States; Yiddish literature; Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography; Electronic mail; Electronic records
Contents of Collection
- Sacvan Bercovitch papers, 1940s-1999, (8 boxes)
  Research notes, manuscripts on paper and floppy diskettes, and some correspondence relating to the serial Cambridge History of American Literature, of which Bercovitch is general editor. Research notes chiefly relate to Bercovitch's work on colonial American literature and religion, particularly on the Puritans in New England, and American humor. Also includes drafts with corrections of A Cultural Model of Literary Studies, and Literary Context, both by Bercovitch. Another set of files consists of writings by others, curriculum vitae, and more correspondence pertaining to the Cambridge serial. Some correspondence and articles date from the 1940s and 1950s and were written by Bryna Bercovitch in Yiddish; English translations included. Some later correspondence is comprised of email printed out. There is also material documenting his work as an English professor at Harvard, such as student correspondence and papers, and material regarding Yiddish literature.
  - Correspondence (professional), 1969, Dec.-1986, Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1987, Feb.-1991, Nov. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1992, Mar.-1994, June (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1994, Aug. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Writings with some Correspondence (professional): Deadpan Trickster (Box 1)
  - Writings with some correspondence (professional) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1995, Nov.-1998, Nov. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1999, Jan.-1999, Mar. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1999, Apr.-1999, May (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (professional), 1999, June-1999, July (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (personal and professional), 1984, Nov.-1999, Mar. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (personal and professional), 1999, Apr.-1999, May (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Bryna Bercovitch: Writings, 1940s (Box 3)
  - Bryna Bercovitch: Writings, 1940s-1950s, including photocopies of original drafts, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Drafts (SB): Fragments, A Literary Approach to Cultural Studies (Box 3)
  - Drafts (SB): Fragments, End-Game Gambit: A Model of Literary and Cultural Studies (Box 3)
  - Drafts (SB): Fragments, A Cultural Model of Literary Studies> (Box 3)
  - Drafts: Fragment, [End-Game Gambit?], undated (Box 3)
  - Drafts: A Cultural Model of Literary Studies, 1994 and undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Nathan Weinstein: Biographical information (Box 4)
  - Culture in a Faulknerian Context (Box 4)
  - The Claims of Rhetoric: Miscellaneous publisher information and outline (Box 4)
  - Drafts: fragment, A Limitless Field: Interdisciplinary Approaches to Literature (keynote address for literary symposium, Texas Christian Univ., 1994; version of "A Cultural Model of Literary Studies" (Box 5)
  - Drafts: fragment, A Cultural Model of Literary Studies, undated, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - Handwritten notes (Box 5)
  - Bryna Bercovitch: Drafts (photocopies of translations), 1946-1950, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Bryna Bercovitch: Rokhel (essay), 1946 (Box 6)
  - Library of America Volume on Nathanael West, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Drafts (Printed from diskettes 1-9), 1993-1994 and undated, (10 folders) (Box 7)
    Includes The Winthrop Variation, Games of Chess: A Model of Cultural Studies, and other variations of the same works, with differing titles.
  - Drafts (Printed from diskettes 10-17), 1993-1994 and undated, (7 folders) (Box 8)
    Includes The Winthrop Variation, and other variants of the same work.
  - Student papers for literature classes (Box 8)
  - Spanish language exam sample (Box 8)
  - Gifts of Faith in the Atonement of Christ - graduate student essay [SB?] (Box 8)
  - Diskettes 1-17 (3.5 floppies) (Box 8)
  - Notecards, citations from literary works by Melville, Douglass, Dewey (Box 8)
- Addition (1999-0261), 1969-1999 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Addition (1999-0261) contains primarily e-mail correspondence with colleagues and students, and drafts of writings, including Deadpan Trickster: The American Humor of Huckleberry Finn. Additional items include clippings, printed materials, and an award.
  - Writings and Correspondence
    - Drafts of Deadpan Trickster: The American Humor of Huckleberry Finn filed with professional correspondence including e-mail (Box 1)
  - Professional Correspondence
    - 1969 Dec. - 1994 Aug. (Box 1)
    - 1995 Nov. - 1999 July (Box 2)
  - Personal and Professional Correspondence
    - 1984 Nov. - 1999 May (Box 2)
  - Additional Materials
    - Printed items and student evaluations (Box 2)
  - Oversize Materials
    - Clippings (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Printed Materials (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Award from the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Opaperfolder 1)
- Addition (2001-0091), 1995-2001, (3 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (01-091) (1700 items, dated 1995-2001) contains primarily e-mail correspondence with colleagues and students. Also includes teaching materials, a 1996 lecture on John Winthrop, and translations of writings (1943-1950) in Yiddish by Bryna Bercovitch.
- Addition (2001-0211), 1991-2001, (2 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (01-211) (1500 items, 1.2 linear feet; dated 1991-2001 and n.d.) consists primarily of email correspondence with colleagues and students (1995-2001). Also includes drafts of writings sent to Bercovitch (1991-1999 and n.d.) and materials relating to a public television series concerning American literature.
- Addition (2002-0097), 2001-2002, (1 box) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (02-097) (375 items, .6 linear feet; dated 2001-2002) consists of professional and personal correspondence, primarily printed email.
- Addition (2002-0255), 2001-2002, (2 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (02-255) (1200 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 2001-2002) contains primarily email correspondence with colleagues, friends, and former students. Also includes publication drafts (undated) by Bercovitch, particularly proofs of Deadpan Huck, which was published in the Kenyon Review, and information about Bercovitch's retirement at the end of 2001.
- Addition (2003-0276), 2001-2003, (6 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (03-276) (2175 items, 3.4 lin. ft.; dated 2001-2003) consists primarily of printouts of email correspondence with colleagues, friends, and former students.
- Addition (2004-0093), 2003-2004, (5 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (04-093) (1500 items, 2.4 lin. ft.; dated 2003-2004) contains primarily printouts of email correspondence with colleagues and friends regarding American literature, Yiddish literature, and other topics.
- Addition (2005-0074), 1983-2005, (12 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (05-074) (4276 items, 7.2 lin. ft.; dated 1983-2005) comprises primarily personal and professional email correspondence (2001-2005); research notes; other correspondence; and teaching materials from courses taught in the 1980s.
- Addition (2006-0057), 2000-2006, (6 boxes) (Opaperfolder 1)
  Addition (06-057) (1,875 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 2000-2006) consists primarily of printouts of email correspondence with colleagues, friends, and former students.
- Additions (2008-0103 and 2009-0145), 1973-2009, (16 boxes)
  Additions (08-103 and 09-145) (7200 items; 9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1973-2009) includes printouts of email correspondence (both professional, personal, and class-related); research/lecture notecards on various books and authors; course packets with articles and readings on Puritans, Jewish-American literature, and general American literature; reviews of some of Bercovitch's books; materials from the publication of The Art of Sylvia Ary; and miscellaneous teaching materials and articles.
  Although this addition has not been processed, materials have been arranged into loose series: Correspondence, Book Reviews, Materials from The Art of Sylvia Ary, Teaching Materials, and Research/Lecture Notes. Correspondence consists almost entirely of email printouts, and various folders have been marked as professional or personal when assigned as such by Bercovitch. The addition originally contained seven CDs and one floppy disk from The Art of Sylvia Ary; these materials have been copied to the library server, and the disks have been transferred to the custody of the Electronic Records Archivist.
  - Email correspondence, 2006 (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - Email correspondence, 2006-2007 (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - Email correspondence, 2007 (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - Email correspondence, 2007 (7 folders) (Box 4)
  - Email correspondence, 2007-2008 (8 folders) (Box 5)
  - Email correspondence, 2006-2008 (10 folders) (Box 6)
  - Email correspondence, February 2008-August 2008 (9 folders) (Box 7)
  - Email correspondence, September 2008-February 2009 (10 folders) (Box 8)
  - Email correspondence, February 2009-May 2009 (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - Correspondence and drafts of correspondence, 1994-2001 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2000-2008 (Box 9)
  - Professional email correspondence, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 9)
  - Financial (Box 9)
  - Seminar email correspondence, Spring 2009 (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Class email correspondence, September 2008-January 2009 (7 folders) (Box 10)
  - Reviews (Box 11)
    - Puritan Origins of the American Self (1975), 1975-1976 (Box 11)
    - Reconstructing American Literary History (1986), 1986-1988 (Box 11)
    - Ideology and Classic American Literature (1986), 1986-1987 (Box 11)
    - Typology and Early American Literature (1972), 1973-1986 (Box 11)
    - American Puritan Imagination (1974), 1974-1976 (Box 11)
    - Cambridge History of American Literature (1994), 1995-1998 (Box 11)
    - The American Jeremiad (1978), 1978-1989 (Box 11)
    - The Rites of Assent (1992), 1993-1995 (Box 11)
    - The Office of the Scarlett Letter (1991), 1992-1998 (Box 11)
  - Datebook, 2006 (Box 11)
  - The Art of Sylvia Ary
    - 7 compact discs, 1 floppy disk (Box 11)
      These disks have been separated from the collection and are available through Duke's Electronic Records server. See Research Services for assistance.
    - Drafts and correspondence (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Email correspondence, 2008 (5 folders) (Box 12)
    - Correspondence and notes (Box 12)
    - Final copy (Box 12)
    - English text (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Illustrations (Box 12)
    - French text (Box 12)
    - Cover (Box 12)
    - Proofs and drafts (Box 12)
    - Street scenes (Box 13)
    - Still lifes: not used (Box 13)
    - The Actors, 1980: not used (Box 13)
    - Kubla Khan silkscreen: not used (Box 13)
    - Portraits: not used (Box 13)
    - Various photographs and transparencies (Box 13)
    - Artwork and figures (Box 13)
    - Extra transparencies and photographs (Box 13)
    - Publishers (Box 13)
    - Book final (Box 13)
    - English draft (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - French text (Box 13)
    - Book proofs with edits (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Teaching matierals
    - Supplement to American Literary History (Box 13)
    - Emerson binder (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Sourcebook binder (1 of 2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Sourcebook binder (2 of 2 folders) (Box 14)
    - The Myth of America, 1993 (Box 14)
    - New England Puritanism, 1993 (Box 14)
    - Hawthorne and Literary History sourcebooks (Box 14)
    - American Identities, 1997 (Box 14)
    - Three Modern Jewish Writers coursepack (Box 14)
    - General teaching materials (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Puritanism in America, 1999 (Box 15)
    - Articles (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Research/lecture notes
    - American Revolution (Box 15)
    - Bellamy (Box 15)
    - Douglass (Box 15)
    - Emerson (Box 15)
    - Emerson and miscellaneous (Box 15)
    - Emerson and Self-Reliance (Box 15)
    - Huck Finn (Box 15)
    - Kerovac (Box 15)
    - King (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Mailer (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Scarlett Letter (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Steinbeck (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Twain (Box 15)
  - Professional papers (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - American Literature to 1860 coursebooks, 2000 (2 versions) (Box 16)
  - Sourcebooks (2 versions) (Box 16)
  - English 17, 1999 (Box 16)
  - Syllabus materials (Box 16)
  - Isaac Babel biography (Box 16)
- Accession (2010-0036), (3 boxes)
  Correspondence, lectures, and lecture notes about various English literature authors.
  - Personal correspondence, 2008 (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Lecture/author notes and notecards
    - Faulkner (Box 1)
    - Absalom (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald (Box 1)
    - Morrison (Box 1)
    - J.D. Salinger (Box 1)
    - The Scarlet Letter (Box 1)
    - Edgar Allen Poe (Box 1)
    - The Great Gatsby (Box 2)
    - Hemingway (Box 2)
    - Robinson Housekeeping (Box 2)
    - West: Miss Lonelyhearts and The Day of the Locust (Box 2)
  - Puritanism notes (Box 2)
  - Lectures, 1995-2001 (Box 2)
  - Edwards notes (Box 2)
  - Seminar 2009 emails (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Seminar 2009 emails (6 folders) (Box 3)
- Accession (2011-0082) 1956-2010 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Series consists of three subseries. The Books Subseries includes fourteen published works with Bercovitch's notations in the margins. Correspondence Subseries consists of one folder with letters ranging from 2002 to 2010. The bulk of the letter are from past students. The Printed Material Subseries holds two articles; one from 1967 entitled Teenager's resentment dissolves in foster home and an article published in the New York Times on March 28, 2010 titled Mad As Hell. And...
  - Books Subseries, 1956-1979 and undated
    Subseries consists of 14 books with Bercovitch's annotations.
    - (Box 1)
    - Bellamy, Edward. Looking Backward: 2000-1887. New York: Hendricks House, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Blau, Joseph L., ed. Social Theories of Jacksonian Democracy. Indianapolis: The Bobbs-Merrill Company, Inc., 1975. (Box 1)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne. Adventures of Huckleberry Finn. San Francisco: Chandler Publishing Company, 1962. (Box 1)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne. A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court. San Francisco: Chandler Publishing Company, 1963. (Box 1)
    - Douglass, Frederick. Narrative of the Life of Frederick Douglass, An American Slave, Written by Himself. New York: Signet, 1968. (Box 1)
    - Emerson, Ralph Waldo. Selections from Ralph Waldo Emerson. Edited by Stephen E. Whicher. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1957. (Box 1)
    - Greene, Jack P., ed. The Reinterpretation of the American Revolution: 1763-1789. New York: Harper & Row, 1968. (Box 1)
    - Hamilton, Alexander, James Madison, John Jay. The Federalist Papers. New York: Mentor, 1961. (Box 1)
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel. The Scarlet Letter. New York: Penguin Books, 1970. (Box 1)
    - (Box 2)
    - Hemingway, Ernest. A Farewell to Arms. New York: Scribner Books. (Box 2)
    - Melville, Herman. Great Short Works of Herman Melville. Edited by Warner Berthoff. New York: Harper & Row, 1969. (Box 2)
    - Melville, Herman. White Jacket or The World in a Man of War. New York: Signet Classic, 1979. (Box 2)
    - Poe, Edgar Allan. Selected Writings of Edgar Allan Poe. Edited by Edward H. Davidson. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1956. (Box 2)
    - Steinbeck, John. The Grapes of Wrath. New York: Penguin Books, 1976. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 2002-2010 and undated
    - Correspondence, 2002-2010 and undated (Box 2)
  - Printed Material Subseries, 1967-2010
    - Newspaper clippings, 1967 and 2010 (Box 2)
- Accession (2011-1008), (1 box)
  Series includes class and lecture notes on a wide range of American authors and novels, as well as a small amount of material related to Bercovitch's writings, including Game of Chess and American Jeremiad. The lecture notes have been arranged alphabetically using Bercovitch's original naming scheme.
  - Lecture notes (Box 1)
    - Bellamy (Box 1)
    - Cather (Box 1)
    - Confidence-Man (Box 1)
    - Declaration of Independence (Box 1)
    - Easy Rider (Box 1)
    - Emerson (Box 1)
    - Enlightenment/Myth (Box 1)
    - Farewell to Arms (Box 1)
    - Hawthorne (Box 1)
    - Hawthorne/Melville (Box 1)
    - House of Seven Gables (Box 1)
    - Huck Finn (Box 1)
    - Henry James (Box 1)
    - Mailer (Box 1)
    - Marble Farm (Box 1)
    - Melville/Emerson (Box 1)
    - Melville, general (Box 1)
    - Melville, Typee (Box 1)
    - Myth, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Pierre, American Myth (Box 1)
    - Pierre, extra (Box 1)
    - Prairie - James Fenimore Cooper (Box 1)
    - Redburn (Box 1)
    - Robinson (Box 1)
    - Salinger (Box 1)
    - Short stories (Box 1)
    - Steinbeck (Box 1)
    - Stowe (Box 1)
    - The Spy (Box 1)
    - Thoreau (Box 1)
    - Thoreau - Puritans (Box 1)
    - White Jacket (Box 1)
    - Unidentified notes (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
    - Game of Chess correspondence, 1995-1999 (Box 1)
    - Game of Chess notes and research, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - The American Jeremiad preface and notes, 2011, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Electronic files
    [Electronic records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - Correspondence for new edition of Puritan Origins of the American Self, 2010-2011, (2 folders, 268 files, 16.9 MB) (Box 1, Efolder E-folder)
    - Preface to new edition of The American Jeremiad, 2012, (22 folders, 294 files, 86.5 MB) (Box 1, Efolder E-folder)
    - American Jeremiad articles, (2 folders, 80 files, 21.5 MB) (Box 1, Efolder E-folder)
    - Courses taught, 1998-2006: American Dissent, College, Extensions, (5 folders, 25 files, 21.2 MB) (Box 1, Efolder E-folder)